<TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">


    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>BHDE - Book 1 - Autograph variants</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id='psn-s.smets'>Simon Smets</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcriber</resp>
                    <name xml:id='psn-m.petolicchio'>Marco Petolicchio</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Not ​for ​distribution.​</p>
            </publicationStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    
    
    <text>
    
        <body xml:id='701' xml:lang='en'>

<seg target='#101001'>
Speak, Muse, of the arms of fierce Mars and of the victory won by the bravery of a magnanimous man. Fearless and with courageous deeds, he drove away the Iberians who had marched up to the Tyrrhenian shores. For it was not just that the Latin people should perish 
</seg>
<seg target='#101005'>
 and that the men should serve a foreign tyrant. What anxiety drove the barbarians and Italian people, determined to fight, to start a new war? What cause persuaded them to provoke savage Mars? What brought both peoples 
</seg>
<seg target='#101010'>
 to bear an eternal hatred and to rise up in such anger? Age-old loyalty and Strife that keeps alive the memory of the ancient past. So much sea and land had Roman rule, raised through her power, once put under her feet: the land of the Garamantes and the Africans, the East and West, the North and South, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101015'>
 and she had subjugated the conquered earth. As a consequence, discord constantly flows on from far away 
but urged by fate
, agitated anger mixes with mighty incitements, madness increases across all the lands, and the unreliable Iberians reproach the Roman rulers 
</seg>
<seg target='#101020'>
 for having plundered faraway regions. Then, at last, the moment calls for attacking the weakened ruins of Latium and its battling souls. They saw the cruel war as Italy’s common wrong. Every Ligurian and Euganean was under arms. As the barbarian people had appointed a powerful king 
</seg>
<seg target='#101025'>
, they went and claimed the Italian lands for themselves. Now does illustrious fame rouse the men, honour grows to full strength, and now are the hastening people carried by a love for ancient praise. Now do they remind each other of the deeds of their forefathers and become incandescent with flickering ardour. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101030'>
 Another result is the Ausonian honour and excessive pride in old power and divine favours. These had been dedicated to the Latin cause as long as flourishing Italy fought her wars far away from home. Here, too, is the Roman virtue of men from the past. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101035'>
 For many years already, wonders from the Gods have been showing signs of what is to come, and they threaten with slaughter and cruel devastation as the earth trembles. Internal conflicts between the people began to rise, and many lives were restored to death, their threads cut through by the Parcae. At the pole were eclipses of the Sun, the Moon reverted her course, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101040'>
 there were frightful appearances, and stars fell from heaven. Even then, all these signs already predicted the war that was at hand and prepared for death and manslaughter. For fierce Alfonso was coming to the Ausonian lands, and by disembarking his savage people on the Tyrrhenian shores, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101045'>
 he frightened the Etruscans with his arrival and reputation. Then, in heaven on high, the father of Gods himself, the son of Saturn, calls for Mercury, who carries the words and orders of the father through the thin air: “Cyllenian offspring, son, fly and descend quickly from clear Olympus. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101050'>
 Command Sigismondo, who is now wasting much time, to rally all the peoples of Italy and force back Alfonso from the shores of his fatherland. Although the latter excels in warfare and once subjected Parthenope to his arms, he shall flee. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101055'>
 With swift south winds, he shall put the curved sails to the seafaring mast.” So he spoke, and Mercury puts on his beautiful sandals and binds on his breezing wings with agile feathers. Then he takes his wand and his customary cap, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101060'>
 and going down steadfastly, he moved away from heaven. He navigates the etherial skies and leaves vast Olympus behind. Apollo sent a favourable west wind to help him from a distance. With these summoned winds, he eventually reached the tents of great Pandolfo, who, in the middle of that night, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101065'>
 took divine rest and was snatching some pleasant sleep. “Hey!” he says, “Does the greatest leader of the Italians keep guard? The father of the gods, who makes the seas, the earth and the golden stars go round, sends me to you from highest Olympus. He orders you to lead the Latins from every tribe against the Celts. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101070'>
 All the gods are in favour – even loftiest Juno will be with you everywhere.” So he spoke and, rising into the swift air, he left the young man wondering about such a message. Pandolfo ponders much over the orders from Jove, and various sorrows pass through his heart. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101075'>
 He silently goes over them one by one. He recalls from his mournful breast first what had happened so far: the assiduous sufferings of war and the decrees of the gods. He then changed his mind in every possible direction to what fortune brings at this moment, and in what way relief could surely follow, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101080'>
 and he feared for all the dangers that threatened his fatherland. He stands up, puts on his fine tunic, a purple cloak, and on top of that wraps himself in a gold-threaded chlamys and laces up his boots on his feet. At the same time, he takes his shining sword, remarkable for its gems and marvellous gold 
</seg>
<seg target='#101085'>
 and covered with images. Vulcan himself had made it for him and had thrust it with a hiss into the flaming waves. Then, he takes his sceptre, which the Omnipotent had once given to Pandolfo as an outstanding gift, and with which he kept hold of a large kingdom and ruled peoples and cities of the Italians. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101090'>
 Girded with those things, the heroic son of Pandolfo steps forth, shining from a high hill and elevated above all. He calls Chalcobous and Eurybromus, to whom he gives the following orders: “Heralds, cared for by great Jove and men, go immediately to Alfonso and quickly bring him my message. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101095'>
 No shadowy mountains nor sounding sea divide us: The two of us shall meet at arms on a plain field. It is not I who decided to pursue wicked wars against him or to depart my fatherland, eager for power. A great unsettling injustice 
</seg>
<seg target='#101100'>
 compelled me to provoke war in a battle on the Etruscan fields. The Ausonian race and the shores of the spoiled land solicit me and force me to wage a new war. He should retreat and eventually leave what he has wrongly plundered in vain. Then I will leave the Maeonian shores as a guest. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101105'>
 If, however, he prepares to defy the pride of the Ausonians, as well as our courage, I will take matters into my own hands. Neither will I be reluctant to wage war until I will have led the Italians to the odious shores of Tarragona.” Such was the message he ordered to be sent to the great tyrant. 
In the meantime, Aurora had driven her sleek chariot over the ocean. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101110'>
 She sprinkled new light over the trembling waves of the sea and set alight the highest mountains with her torch. Pandolfo stood still, and watching the new light of the great Sun, he prayed. “Sun, who sees everything and, in your loftiness, hears all! Best archer among the gods! Apollo, who lives in Chrysa! 
</seg>
<seg target='#101115'>
 You who hold the happy realms of Cylla and Tenedos, your Delos, the founts of Ortygia, the mountains of Cynthus and hollow Eurotas, Lycia, Soracte’s heights in Hesperia and the Capitoline hills of high Rome! Most beautiful among the gods, favour our undertakings.” 
</seg>
<seg target='#101120'>
 After he spoke thus, he mounts his horse with checked reins and explores the ways, the uncultivated rocks, the difficult places and those that appear easy at sight, the sounding Arno and other Etruscan rivers as well as the fresh green woods. Like when a tawny lion stands savage on top of the Phoenician mountains, when a hunter chases it 
</seg>
<seg target='#101125'>
 through rocky valleys and malicious paths. It has roared thrice between its white teeth, murmured and provoked fear with its fierce mouth. The African man nevertheless hunts the irritated animal, exhausts it with projectiles, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101130'>
 while pursuing it all the way, and follows its track through dark woods. In the same manner, the heroic son of Pandolfo chases king Alfonso and prevents him from resting in the camps that are set up. The Italian peoples gather around him and fill his mind with welcome joy with gentle words. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101135'>
 Pallas was his enviable ally, and she bestowed him with immortal lustre, while supporting him in strength and spirit. The beloved child of Jove, the Tritonian goddess, displays in the middle of the battlefield the snakes and hissing mouth of the gorgon Medusa, the fearsome Aegis with horrors of bronze, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101140'>
 the arms of cloud-borne Jove, by means of which he destroys cities to the ground. Exhorting the men, she puts into the minds of all war only and a sweet love for Mars. The men no longer desire their fatherland or dear penates, but only war. War! All their love goes out to warfare. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101145'>
 The Italians rumble their arms, the excited land resounds with horrendous tumult, and the men shine with gold and tawny copper. As when fire rages through a dense forest and spreads roaring flames far and wide, a reddish gleam becomes visible in the high mountains, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101150'>
 and fires produce light spread over innumerable places, Vulcan flickers hence and thence. Just so the rising sun at its highest point gave light that was broken up by the bronze in flashing rays, and the new light filled everything alike as it was doubled by the reflection of the flames. 
As when many thousands of the countless breed of birds 
</seg>
<seg target='#101155'>
 now quickly come to you on serried wings, Mantua, as your swamps resound with loud rumour, and father Mincio welcomes long cohorts on his banks, or clouds of swans are often driven over the Asian meadow and over the flaxen fields of the Cayster to the shores 
</seg>
<seg target='#101160'>
 – the birds play with shrieking noise in the skies – just so do the many strong Italians now come together from all the cities around towards the camp and the stream of the flowing Arno. Here Sigismondo, in his beautiful armour, took up a position in the middle of the camp and his men. Many thousand men 
</seg>
<seg target='#101165'>
 from hither and thither stand around him in formation – also young men who girded their sword as if a total frenzy calls to the savage fighting of stern Mars. From everywhere, noise, and from everywhere people assemble. They admire him and from the first to the last, they come to him. As when 
</seg>
<seg target='#101170'>
 a murmur slowly rises from the rolling waves of the deep sea, the South and West winds howl around unyielding rock, the stream beats against it, the sea rages, the whole large surface of the ocean swells faster and faster, white froth splashes up from the reverberating surface of the sea, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101175'>
 all the waves throw themselves one after another on the rocks with countless swells, Orion is beaten by dark storm-clouds and, flying into a cloud, hides his head in the sky and his feet underneath the earth. 
Just so do the many strong Italians form noiseless 
</seg>
<seg target='#101180'>
 lines, as their leader with his right hand gives the sign to stand in silence. Nobody would think that in the mortal hearts of all these people lies the ability to speak. Now they took no pleasure in talking, not even in the pleasant conversation among comrades. Such was their quietude of mind, and such an honour it was to obey. The whole day long, dense formations continued to arrive in the same 
</seg>
<seg target='#101185'>
 order, and they do not stop until the dark night overwhelms the men’s strength and convinces them to prepare for welcome rest. At that moment, Venus spoke thus to ambrosial Sleep: 
“Sleep! Rest of the gods! You divine pleasure of mankind, who refresh bodies weighed down by all kinds of weaknesses 
</seg>
<seg target='#101190'>
 and relieve mankind of its burning sorrows! Do you see how only Sigismondo himself stands in his beautiful armour, deeply concerned about the reputation of his beloved fatherland? A pious and illustrious man, he comes with a ready army from the lands of Rimini to look after the Etruscan cities, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101195'>
 and now he deploys on the dear shores of Lydia. Go, Sleep, go pour godly rest into the tired bones of the young man and let it seep throughout his mind. Here, gifts await you that are worthy of such a service. For the most beautiful among our Graces will be given to you 
</seg>
<seg target='#101200'>
 as a pleasant wife. She would be dedicated to the marital bond as an enviable joy for years without end. Enjoy a splendid marriage with Pasithea. Do not hope that Juno can give you any of my nymphs, nor could the King of the gods himself 
</seg>
<seg target='#101205'>
 turn the Acidalian maidens from our fount, even if he wanted to.” 
She had spoken, and he frees his heavy wings from their slow torpor and, gently wrapped in dark clouds, he flies off to where the Arno at its largest point turns its flowing waves and looks up at the woods from its fresh green border. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101210'>
 As he finds him considering various matters in his heart and considering many events during much of the night, without sleep in his eyes but observing everything that could happen in the future, he asks: “Why, Pandolfo, do you not lay down your head and refresh yourself? Why do you forbid yourself from submitting to pleasant rest?” 
</seg>
<seg target='#101215'>
 He spoke thus, and he poured out a mighty and godly sleep deep into his breast. The heroic son of Pandolfo, overcome by the agile god, lay down his exhausted limbs and deep in his heart forgetfulness of great matters takes over. 
Then the omnipotent father takes care of another, more fruitful 
</seg>
<seg target='#101220'>
 aid for him and immediately calls for multi-coloured Iris. “Iris, do you see with what slaughter and destruction the rough King who comes from his Iberian fatherland threatens the Ausonians? The son of Pandolfo prepares to march against him tomorrow, trusting in his fierce arms. He was at last able to stretch his limbs for some late rest, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101225'>
 after sleep had been sent. Bread and even wine are of no avail to him, but he feeds on immense sorrows. I order you to bring him nectar, ambrosia and food pleasing for a divine man to eat. It is his right to know the gifts of the gods, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101230'>
 his right to breathe in divine air.” 
This he said, and the great goddess did not object, but set off from heaven, very quickly descending from the top of the high pole towards the camps of the Etruscans with a swift leap. She perceives armed men eating here and there on the grass 
</seg>
<seg target='#101235'>
 as well as smoking fireplaces. She sees that scouts have taken position over here, having abandoned their camps, that men are soothing their limbs over there on the ground, close to each other. All of them want to stay where they are as long as possible, regardless of their lot. Then, the goddess poured out divine 
</seg>
<seg target='#101240'>
 solace for his strong limbs deep into the leader’s breast. His former strength immediately filled his great body. A sweet breath of fragrant air was taken in, pulsating just under his lively heart, filled his entire body and renewed the old fires in his bones. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101245'>
 
In the meantime, heralds bring his message to the snow-white tents of King Alfonso. He is not at all astonished by the account and with a forthright voice, he answers: 
“Go, and return in haste, and report from me the following words to your leader. In no way can war against the Italian men 
</seg>
<seg target='#101250'>
 change my course. Notorious battles do not tire me. Parthenope, which was added to my reign after seven years – Jove was on my side – has taught me not to be afraid of such troops as the heroic son of Pandolfo has now led from his fatherland to the Etruscan shores. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101255'>
 Tell him that if he would want, his army could attack with all its arms, in case he prepares to join the Latins against my people. If, however, he wants to conclude the war with our blood, it would be no problem that both of us fight in one confrontation of arms, that both armies stand back so that they can see with their arms put down whom God looks after and 
</seg>
<seg target='#101260'>
 to whom his faithful right hand will award salvation.” They report these words to Pandolfo and unfold everything in order. He, however, promptly salutes them with an expression of joy, thanks Jove and at once starts praying with the following words: 
“May you command so, highest god and savage Mars. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101265'>
 May you, Minerva, now want to call to arms. Rejoice, magnanimous men! For in a courageous attempt, I go into battle one-on-one with King Alfonso, who defies the Italians with unjust aggression. This will at last be the end of the war. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101270'>
 All future people who will want to admire fierce wars will say that I have truly sacrificed one soul, namely mine, for the people of prosperous Italy and that I am worthy of the blood of the ancient forefathers. You, men, nevertheless all put on your rattling arms and march in formation, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101275'>
 noble men, with your sword girded too, as if a total frenzy calls to the savage fighting of stern Mars. Go, troops! Others must bring to light any traps, so that the barbarian throng can nowhere plan hidden ambushes, and so that the enemy cannot conceal any traps to stop us in a valley of hidden retreat.” 
</seg>
<seg target='#101280'>
 
He had finished speaking, but the Italians burst out in a disorganised tumult, and the earth groans very loudly, incited by the great roaring. The noise from the men then starts to mix with the voices of talking people and varied shouts fly through the air. Just so lofty Jove once 
</seg>
<seg target='#101285'>
 thundered from Olympus, and the deafening sound echoed through all slopes. Then do the winds lift the foaming water on the large Icarian sea, and both the South and West winds fall down and now move Nereus from the deepest depths. Sigismondo then stretches out his right hand and ordered the people to be quiet. Now 
</seg>
<seg target='#101290'>
 he looks at these leaders and then he admonishes others. Whenever he catches sight of an unimportant man who shouts with his weapons in hand and spreads a murmur throughout the unmoving crowd, he rebukes and chastises him with severe words like the following: 
“Unfortunate man, what very stupid idea enters your vain mind, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101295'>
 that you don’t want to listen to the words of another? Unwarlike person, not all of us Italians shall rule here. For there is one king, and there should be one leader of the Etruscans. He to whom the omnipotent Father has given the sceptre should rule the Latins with authority.” And having spoken thus, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101300'>
 he hangs his heavy armour around his shoulders, shining in front of everyone with gold that flashes into the distance. As Canis, the shining glory of gilded Orion, twinkles over many stars, fatally rises with hackles raised in the burning heath 
</seg>
<seg target='#101305'>
 and spreads dark diseases among feeble mortals – every kind of animal and those born from mixed blood die, the white dogs in the mountains have died. Just so was golden Sigismondo, flickering in his beautiful armour, while all the troops radiated with yellow metal. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101310'>
 “Let us now try our hand at the forces of sharp warfare, so I can see who should throw with strong spears, who should rather feed the horses with thick fodder, who is better in running and ready for furtive action, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101315'>
 which lighter man should mount a two-horse chariot and put on his arms or grab his helmet and shining shield. I will never stop commanding the people, and least of all today. Until the stars come, night approaches the high sky and, riding her chariot, breaks the strength of men, their courage and anger with burning incentives, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101320'>
 I will order to give to the birds and wild dogs the bodies of everyone I should see withdraw far from the shores. Force the cowards in the middle of the ranks. The brave men should stand before them and the elder should follow at the back.” So he spoke, and all the Latins 
</seg>
<seg target='#101325'>
 shouted out with much clamour, and they spread over the plains and fields. 
Similarly, when the sea-surface rises on rolling waves, the swift winds go through the sounding void, a stormy south-wind from elsewhere makes way on his soaking wings, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101330'>
 when he has been set free from Aeolus’ prison and takes hold of the sea. The sounding waves splash up around the shores, the south-wind then beats against a dangerous crag or the back of a rock, howls loudly and leaves the cliffs behind. 
But flying Rumour had already occupied the savage Iberians with the news that a great leader was coming. Nobody was more successful than he 
</seg>
<seg target='#101335'>
 in the current Italian conflict, nor ever before. Burning sorrow naturally took hold of many down to their bones, with boundless anger added in many cases. Everywhere is much shouting, and strife roams everywhere and upsets the crowd. The courage of the Italians stirs some, the illustrious 
</seg>
<seg target='#101340'>
 fame of such a leader, others, and it stirs Antiphates, who has always been before anyone else the best companion of a single King in the greatest battles. He was skilled with his right hand, and glory resulting from renowned deeds brought him great honour on account of his great courage. He was not less experienced in councils; therefore, his fame was not 
</seg>
<seg target='#101345'>
 futile, which is the primary fault of the vain Iberians. As soon as he caught sight of magnanimous King Alfonso among the troops, he fearlessly addresses him with harsh words. 
“I will tell you something, and you shall please forgive me, highness, if I err. I will now lay out with good will what I have developed in my mind. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101350'>
 You should refrain from trying your hand at the strong arms of Sigismondo. Stop trusting in the actions that you undertook some time ago. Get us away from the raging fortune of the Italians. Because, if you don’t care for your own welfare, at least take pity on your fatherland. Take pity 
</seg>
<seg target='#101355'>
 on the lands in the faraway regions of noble but wavering Hesperia. Why do I hold back? Should perhaps the Italians seize the gods of our fatherland, when dark death takes possession of you? May the deep earth break open for me, may I fall down in the shadows of the Styx, before good Alfonso, dying on the Ausonian shores, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101360'>
 leaves this glory to Italy and the Etruscan peoples. The people that wage great wars for you are strong and ahead of the others, and you have additional troops. You must win through extensive procurement. Both parts of land and sea are in our hands. Why do you fear war, while all of Italy remains inactive? 
</seg>
<seg target='#101365'>
 Or had Sigismondo, in the armour of his forefathers, driven off many people on his own, without a great army?” 
Antiphates had spoken, but with unfriendly words and a frown of disapproval, the grim tyrant spoke to him, who was now trembling with fear. 
“Unfortunate Antiphates, although you have much to say, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101370'>
 stop talking and don’t scold the leaders in front of all the people with that shameless mouth of yours. Oh, shame! So, all those who followed me once, tell me to go back to the forefatherly cities, by Jove! They once promised to face every battle I would call them for, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101375'>
 to surround the houses of the Ausonians with swift flames and to commit themselves to fighting in a long war? Perhaps they are bothered by the delay? The people should remain for the time in which the moon completes a single cycle. Alfonso has decided to put an end to the war. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101380'>
 Don’t make me, your king, an eternal disgrace for all those who are to come. I don’t want to blame you if the long delay is tiring, sons of Hesperia. Lofty Jove has delayed you for many years. However, it would be disgraceful to have returned now to the gods of our fatherland. Companions, endure this final war, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101385'>
 and let us see to it in a short while, that Phorbas, the seer, sings everything in truth. For you have seen, Iberians – we have all seen this – when we covered the sea with many ships and prepared our deadly weapons against the Italians. It isn’t long since 
</seg>
<seg target='#101390'>
 Jasius the priest, covered in golden clothes, lit the holy fires on the altars under the shadowy leaves of an oak with outstretched branches. Close to it, in the woods, a very large pine rises up with its crown trimmed and green branches twined around its peak. A dove has taken seat on top of each tree. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101395'>
 The one that had been sitting on the green pine has been alarmed by the flight of Jove’s arm-bearing bird and hiding in the branches, it concealed itself in the dark foliage. It chases her from all sides, flying seven times around. And while the bird flies its seventh round, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101400'>
 the subdued dove flees and moves through the thin air. Suddenly, Jove’s sacred arm-bearer catches her on an east-wind. Then, he quickly attacks the one that had stayed in the sacred oak. With his bloody nails, he eviscerates the trembling creature and a victor he stands still on the highest peak.” The son of Atlas then said: “Proud people, have hope. From high heaven, Saturn’s son has shown us this end to the war: The seven full circles designate seven years and indicate the seven periods during which the great Iberians continually had to wage war. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101410'>
 But the second one is Italy, whom you will conquer with little effort so your grandchildren will reign over her.” So the son of Atlas said: “Endure what is happening now, noble Iberians, until Saturn’s reign has come, and we have levelled the high cities of Italy to the ground.” 

</seg>
<seg target='#101415'>
 He had spoken, and with loud shouting, all the armed men rushed from the rampart, as when crane birds with hoarse calling fly through the clouds and cross the ice-cold sea, and flocks gather in a large formation, bringing death and evil fate to the Pygmies. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101420'>
 
Yet, the Italians formed silent formations in defence. On the first place before the others stood Sigismondo in his beautiful armour. As when a bull leads the flock from various places into a conflict and defies the winds with his neck raised high, just so did the ruler of Olympus destine you, Pandolfo, to be the glory of the Latin peoples. At that point, the battle lines came close to each other – the Iberians shouting, the Italians in uncanny silence.
Similarly, the south wind drives a dark cloud, which is better than the night for a bandit, but troublesome for a shepherd, onto a sky-scraping mountain. The distance for both sides to reach the front of the other army on the covered field, was as far as someone could throw a spear by hand through the trembling air or send a stone into the air with a spinning sling. All of a sudden, the first ranks become agitated, and a horrifying throng moves over the fields. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101435'>
 They thrash the battlefield and make a raid. Holding a lance, Sigismondo ordered the Italians to withdraw and halt their march. The Celts nevertheless persisted in shooting arrows and throwing round stones through the air, but Alfonso called them back from the gloomy fight. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101440'>
 For he understood that the glorious hero wanted to say something. Then, Pandolfo’s great offspring spoke as follows: 
“You, sons of Hesperia, and you, Latins, listen to this: if the happy victory in our fight will turn over to the Italians, it is agreed that 
</seg>
<seg target='#101445'>
 both the Celts and Iberians born from mixed blood can return to their fatherland’s shores in Tarragona. If, however, fortune, out of hate for the Ausonians, would cast an evil eye on me with an odious blow, if father and king of the gods would kill me, at once deprived of my sight and sweet breath, then the unconquered Iberians would fight hard wars with the Italians. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101450'>
 The omnipotent father knows for whom dark death is at hand.” 
So did the son of Ausonia speak, and the people made a growling sound. Their king stood among them and spoke with harsh words. “If it is permitted, we also ask that you, Iberians and great Ausonians, listen to what Jupiter himself orders to make known. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101455'>
 He favours the sacred tyrant; such a great honour comes from Jove. The Spanish and Ausonian men should confirm their agreement with sacred ceremonies. You, noble men, bring a black sheep here. Bring me a white calf as a sacrifice for the Earth and Sun. We ourselves shall bring 
</seg>
<seg target='#101460'>
 another outstanding lamb for Dis. No bold man shall want to disturb the ceremony for Jove while hiding in the dense army.” He had spoken, but the Latins happily roared from their hearts together with the Spaniards, because they hoped to see the hard war come to an end, which had started long ago and brought no gain at all. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101465'>
 They ride their horses with the reins held tight. The whole crowd throws itself on the ground for them, and the men stand still on the plain field. In between both of them, a space is marked on the ground of the fruitful earth, to set a limit and border for the men. 
At that moment, the father of the gods himself 
</seg>
<seg target='#101470'>
 looks down from high Olympus on the battle lines – with a frown on his head towards the barbarian formations, but with a more positive countenance towards the strong Latins. He says to Juno, who is surrounded by a rainy nimbus and sits on an ice-cold cloud: “Beloved wife, what reason do we have to doubt that there are still people left from the old lineage of the Quirites? 
</seg>
<seg target='#101475'>
 For they are capable of protecting Italy with their strong arms and surpassing the brave deeds of their ancient forefathers. Do you see with what courage Sigismondo rides his foaming horse, and against what enemy he alone presents himself from his early youth, namely alone against Alfonso? 
</seg>
<seg target='#101480'>
 Therefore, since my secrets annoy you, Goddess, learn what idea is on my mind. I now desire to send wind-swift and airy Iris down from the clouds, so the Iberians start first and without notice violate the sacred agreement as soon as the rituals are completed.” 

</seg>
<seg target='#101485'>
 He hardly finished saying this, when bright Juno answers him thus: “We always agree when we disclose our mutual secrets to each other; therefore, you can never give me a greater gift, nor please me more, my dearest. Because I am the first child of my father Saturn, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101490'>
 your descent is the same as mine. I am long since your dedicated lofty wife and your sister, queen of the high gods.” To this, Jove responds: “Your grace has bent me, wife, and you have bound yourself to me with eternal love.” 
So he spoke, and wrapped in a colourful cloud, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101495'>
 she calls the sky-blue goddess. The goddess lays out the orders from the great Thunderer and sends off the airy-footed deity from the high sky. She flies and, driven forwards by a whirlwind, looks back on the lands. She catches sight of the armed battle lines, the peoples shining with bronze from here and there and the formations on the wide fields. 

</seg>
<seg target='#101500'>
 Mars, strong in war, had upset these, and Enyo those. She didn’t pay attention to the men and, leaving everybody aside, went only to Phorbas. In those days, he had been the best at knowing how to understand the councils of all kinds of gods and how to examine dreams in wonderful ways. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101505'>
 By relying on an augury, he alone led Alfonso to the Ausonian shores. Phoebus had bestowed upon him the honour of a seer because, as a child from his youngest years, he had devoted his lute and faith to him. The goddess 
</seg>
<seg target='#101510'>
 hides this old man under the cover of a cloud, away from the people that had returned from each side, and moves him far away into abandoned groves, gloomy places of the woodland. She shows him the peoples that had followed the King, as they give way to an imagined battle formation. The daughter of Thaumas throws such things before the seer by means of false visions 
</seg>
<seg target='#101515'>
 until she leads him away to deserted shores on the coast. She then assumes his features, and the goddess fashions herself like a mortal being. Only a few white hairs stand on the crown of her head, hanging, quivering lips rest on her grey chin, her eyelids tremble and the sound of her trembling voice is 
</seg>
<seg target='#101520'>
 out of tune. Her flanks take in breath in a continuous movement. 
Biaon, a young man from the Libyan race, most skilled with the quiver and rounded arrow, had come with supporting troops. He was used to provoking wild mountain animals and fugacious deer, but also to disturbing tawny lions in a frightening way. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101525'>
 He was covered in the skin of a fierce bear, and his bristly head was covered by the jaws of wolf. In the past, he had made a thousand men tremble with his sharp arrows. When the goddess Iris sees him standing there, she speaks in these words to him, who excels in courage and rages with bravery: 
</seg>
<seg target='#101530'>
 
“Glory of Libyan manhood, Biaon, where are your arrows that were once sure of their goal? Where has the renown of your glory been cast, for which you were used to yield to no-one in Libya? Where are your bows that once distinguished themselves during hunts? Come on – shoot! Phoebus supports you. Strive as the first for beautiful honour. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101535'>
 Take the initiative! What you do shall be welcomed by all the Celts. Above all it will please king Alfonso, if by your astuteness Sigismondo dies dressed up in his armour.” 
Speaking thus, she turns the mind of the frenzied man towards fighting, and he does not think about the unknown 
</seg>
<seg target='#101540'>
 decisions of the Gods, nor about the strength of the Italians or the war against these powerful men. 
In the meantime, the Ausonians and Tarragonian youth gathered towards the middle. After praying to the gods and goddesses, they carry out the sacred rituals and light the sacred altars with fires. Then, the audacious king, come from faraway shores, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101545'>
 stood still and consecrated cups of Ogygian wine. He drank first from the bowl foaming with sweet gifts of the fruitful soil, and the sweet gift of great Silenus’s pupil burnt more than sweet nectar in the pure golden cup. He further ordered gasping entrails, reflecting much on his reign – but neither the entrails, nor the altars nor the gods are of any help to him. At the same time, he starts praying in the following way: 
“If I should breach this agreement with my bare hand or with arms, may someone else’s hand then separate this head from my hacked neck and carry it in triumph to foreign regions.” 

</seg>
<seg target='#101555'>
 He had hardly said this, when the son of Ausonia replied to this with the following words: “Jupiter, most sacred guardian of the Etruscan woodlands, you who reign in the high sky! May the Sun not leave the sky and sink in the rolling waves of the ocean before the Iberians flee, conquered on the Tyrrhenian shore. Also allow 
</seg>
<seg target='#101560'>
 to disgrace Alfonso’s head on the blood-soaked soil, when it is knocked off by our hands, highest among the gods. Allow, Father, to drag his groomed hairs through the dust, his hairs that are perfumed with myrrh and bound with a piece of bright metal. Give that these bandits leave Italy which they have occupied. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101565'>
 Give that the Italians no longer fear the Celts on land or sea. To you, then will I erect churches of white marble, arising with marvellous decoration, admirable for their manifold embellishments. I will dedicate a church to you in the middle of the city of Rimini, at which every barbarian 
</seg>
<seg target='#101570'>
 and Italian will marvel. Allow us to overcome and put an end to this disgrace.” He spoke and sprinkled sweet wine from the bowl on the ground and briefly warns in these words: 
“May the crushed seat of smitten brains of whoever breaches first the pious agreement with weapons 
</seg>
<seg target='#101575'>
 or his bare hand, fall as deep as wine falls in the moistened grass, never to flow back into the bottles.” 
With such words, the armed men vouched for the agreement in front of the altars, and they roared with the confused shouting of men. There was no delay. Headlong and not yet afraid, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101580'>
 the mighty Malatesta from this side and the Tarragonian hero from the other side both stepped forth to the space in between the sons of Hesperia and the Italians, dreadful to see as they beat their rising helmets topped with plumes and decorated with patterns and gold. A strong stupor takes hold of all the peoples watching. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101585'>
 Deep inside, they are resentful and, murmuring, they resist the fierce suffering of a doubtful fight. They threaten each other with many wounds and hurl their arms against each other with mutual blows. 
As when a foreign bull heads towards a large forest, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101590'>
 here and there pursuing alien fields across desolate woodland, draws the flock through various places and thus plunders far and wide the desired farming fields. Every crude farmer is afraid, and the other young bulls flee into the mountains, for, being the strongest, he dominates the ancient forests. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101595'>
 A fierce and hostile bull, after he has sensed that his pasture fields are being occupied, opposes his enemy quite brutally. Then, the alarmed cows keep silent and so do their herdsmen. Just so, the mighty honour of Tarragona and the glory of great Italy circle around each other with unyielding arms. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101600'>
 
As Alfonso now truly considers the force of his sharp spear as usual, by means of which he had sent many to the Stygian underworld, he throws it. In its flight, it struck the border of the seven-layered shield and dangled in the middle stud with a shrill sound. The son of Ausonia didn’t take that and threw the shield away. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101605'>
 As, on the ground, the spear broke off the shield, he himself also fiercely flung with his hand a penetrating spear at the king. It broke the upper part of the shield and tasted the large body, as his breast was slightly wounded. The Italians shout in support and lift a joyful 
</seg>
<seg target='#101610'>
 roar to the stars, but stupefaction makes the knees of all the Spaniards weak. Now, the unquestionable glory of the Malatesta family, the magnanimous son of Pandolfo, trusts in his unyielding arms. He stands firm on his two feet, swift as lightning, and looks at his applauding companions with his head lifted. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101615'>
 He burdens his hand with a violent sword, and wounds his enemy three, four times as the swords are moved in circles. Then swift Sigismondo rises on the tips of his toes and from above turns himself towards downward blows. He redoubles his blows, and gasping for breath, hits from either side on 
</seg>
<seg target='#101620'>
 the glowing helmet, decorated with patterns and gold. After the beaver has almost come loose from the helmet, however, he hits three times more. But when now he breaks the strength of his fatigued sword on the heavy bronze for a fourth time, the sword shatters in the midst of a blow. It unexpectedly falls to pieces, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101625'>
 and so, the fragments deflect off the top of his upper arm. Not deterred by his broken sword or the loss of his arms, the young man runs more eagerly into the fight and, fierce with anger, encourages himself. With his right hand, he aims at the king who is threatening with deep wounds. Now, he strangles his throat with cramped hands, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101630'>
 then he keeps hold of the helmet and pushes on its cone-shaped top. Under the pressing arms, Alfonso could not take in air nor seize upon the sky, but he is dragged like prey worthy of mighty Sigismondo’s hands. Terrified, he nevertheless speaks in the uneasy darkness: 
“Greatest leader of the Italians, to whom Jove himself 
</seg>
<seg target='#101635'>
 and rapidly changing Fortune force me to pray! By their gift, you can consider me a conquered King. Spare me more hatred. I beg you, highness, to leave me alive. Willingly yielding to a conqueror, I leave you all the realms that are mine, extending over various regions.” 
</seg>
<seg target='#101640'>
 
So he spoke, and the heroic son of Pandolfo answers him: “Stop yielding to my arms the realms which you boast are the best and great in number. Now first drag yourself before the proud peoples of Italy and our tents. There, if I’m right, I will see to it that you make a new treaty.” 
</seg>
<seg target='#101645'>
 He had spoken and with both his hands he hauled the wretched King, who was suffering woeful sorrows in his heart. But from afar, Biaon prepares himself with list and much fraud for the well-known means to breach a treaty. They say that he, inflamed by divine power and anger, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101650'>
 took the wicked arms and detestable arrows in his hand. The left hand of the man touched the bow. His quick right hand touched his left nipple. The first shaft, holding on to the hand, touched the sounding string. The swift point of the arrow touched the left hand as well as the bow, and it went with a screeching sound through the awful air. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101655'>
 It arrived and fixed itself in the noble body of great Sigismondo, and the winged projectile dangled from his right upper arm. Immediately, a most powerful pain takes hold of the great body. He almost falls down, the king sets himself loose from his hand and, freed, goes all the way to the Iberians, who are delighted by the breached treaty. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101660'>
 After the pain settled in his inner bones, the son of Pandolfo now speaks with a deplorable voice in the following manner: 
“O almighty Father, if you granted me a deplorably short time of life, you should have bestowed it with more honour. Will you not keep the king from escaping death from my hand? 
</seg>
<seg target='#101665'>
 Or shall I expect this treaty to be free from other deceptions? I would have believed everything which the horrid south wind now blows into the thin air. Did I think it seemly to trust the dreadful Celts and to bind myself with sacred vows to a criminal people? You, highest among the gods, who consecrate treaties with a threefold 
</seg>
<seg target='#101670'>
 lightning, who are able to punish savage tyrants! You, who are mighty, have an eye for the mischance of mortals and confirm the treaty with your right hand.” That was all, and wounded, he drew himself back. Great Apollo, the son of great Jove, stood by him. As a guide, seen by no-one else, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101675'>
 he led with his own hand the young man to his companions. Pandolfo’s most mighty offspring was astonished by what he saw.
“Who of the gods are you who, sent from bright Olympus, came to earth in order to see, I imagine, our suffering, while earlier reposing in heaven on high?” 
</seg>
<seg target='#101680'>
 The son of Jove and Latona answered him in briefly: 
“I am lofty Apollo, the child of great Jove. Being a righteous god, I surely will not leave you unavenged. Your great victory will send you with remarkable glory to the peoples. You would have gained victory on that battlefield, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101685'>
 when you met the King in a one-to-one fight. You will be the winner when leading all the troops to battle.” Apollo, the great son of great Jove, had said this. 
“You have brought this message, which pleases us much, Phoebus. It entirely comes from Jove, Father. However, a serious injury still 
</seg>
<seg target='#101690'>
 holds me down without defence. Why do you not send Paeon down from bright Olympus, who helps mortals with his medical skills? But he must come with father Jove’s consent and on his explicit order, so that the infuriated Father will not thrust him into the stygian water as in the past. You remember everything, 
</seg>
<seg target='#101695'>
 and to remember renews the pain. Broken wheels once dispersed a young man on the curved shore, as his swift horses were frightened by sea-monsters. They tore Hippolytus to pieces after scattering the chariot in a tumultuous moment. Although he was dead, your son then called him back from the stygian underworld. 
</seg>
<seg target='#101700'>
 The almighty one, however, was so furious that he hurled him with a terrific flash into the shallow stream of the Styx. Therefore, it is just to learn first what the opinion of great Jove is and then, Father, you must place me in the sacred arms of your son Paeon. It might help me to have worn a laurel wreath 
</seg>
<seg target='#101705'>
 and to have engaged fully in the arts of the gracious sisters.” The Cynthian god answers him with a pleased voice: 
“Jupiter first goes to the borders of the pious Ethiopians to visit Oceanus for a feast meal. In twelve days – and he won’t be delayed any longer – he will go to Olympus, where his house is continuously frequented by the gods. Then, I can find out what the decision of the magnanimous king is and give his orders to my son.” This said the great son of great Jove, Apollo.
</seg>

END OF THE FIRST BOOK OF BASINIO DA PARMA’S HESPERIS




        </body>
    
    
    </text>


</TEI>